Guide to the Jim Douglas Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Jim Douglas papers
approximately 1973-1991
1983-1989
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
5906
5906-001
Douglas, Jim$d1946-2017
3.32 cubic feet 5 boxes
6 videocassettes (VHS)
Documents the work of Jim Douglas, attorney at law, and affiliated organizations
Jim Douglas is an attorney who has practiced Social Security disability law since 1978. Douglas was part of a legal team working for the families of slain Seattle labor unionists Silme Domingo and Gene Viernes in a civil suit against Philippines dictator Ferdinand Marcos for orchestrating the 1981 assassinations of the union reformers in their Pioneer Square office. The two men had been working with an international community in opposition of the dictator, who had cracked down on the political left and trade unions in the Phillippines when we seized power and declared martial law.
In December of 1989, a jury found that Ferdinand and Imelda Marcos were responsible for the murders and awarded $15 million to the families of Domingo and Viernes. This marked the first time that a foreign dictator was held responsible for crimes committed in the United States.
Douglas was also a co-founder of the Seattle chapter of Line of March, a Marxist-Leninist national political organization in the 1980s dedicated to peace and social justice.
Records created and collected by Douglas as part of a legal team working for the families of Domingo and Viernes in their civil suit against Philippines dictator Ferdinand Marcos. Other records in the collection relate to the Committee for Justice for Domingo and Viernes and Douglas' membership and participation in the founding of the Seattle chapter of Line of March, a Marxist-Leninist national political organization in the 1980s dedicated to peace and social justice.
Records from Jim Douglas' visit as part of a delegation from the National Lawyers Guild to look at the first elections in Nicaragua under the Sandinistas, including several files on the elections, including the delegation's report. Other subjects in the records include Miskito Indians sovereignty rights vs the Sandinistas.
Other records include Douglas' involvement in organizing a Citizens' Tribunal on US Involvement in Central America and the Caribbean from the early 1980s. Records include witness statements from the tribunals as well as 6 VHS videos of the tribunal proceedings.
Textual materials are open to all users. No user access copy is available for the VHS video cassettes. Contact Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries for more information regarding access to video recordings.
Jim Douglas, 2015.
Issues of the newspaper "FrontLine" that span 1983-1990 as well as Crossroads magazine, published by the Institute for Social and Economic Studies, were removed from the manuscript collection to be cataloged as serials. Some monographs were likewise pulled to be cataloged.
Douglas, Jim,$d1946-2017$vArchives; Real Change (Organization)$xOfficials and employees; Douglas Drachler McKee and Gilbrough$xOfficials and employees; Seattle Labor Chorus; International courts; Social security$xLaw and legislation; Trial and arbitral proceedings; Records (Documents); Business correspondence; Interviews; Depositions; Domingo, Silme,$d -1981; Viernes, Gene,$d -1981; Marcos, Ferdinand E.$q(Ferdinand Edralin),$d1917-1989; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Civil Procedure and Courts
- Papers, 1973-1990
  - Line of March (LOM) Related Records, approximately 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Reports and Correspondence, approximately 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Forums and Discussions Related to Seattle LOM, approximately 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Frontline related materials, approximately 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Forums and Discussions Related to Seattle LOM, approximately 1973-1991 (Box 2)
  - Frontline related Materials, approximately 1973-1991 (Box 2)
  - Committee for Justice for Domingo Viernes (CJDV) Records, approximately 1973-1991 (Box 2)
  - Domingo v. Marcos records, approximately 1973-1991 (Box 2)
  - CJDV Records, approximately 1981-1986 (Box 3)
  - Domingo v. Marcos Records, approximately 1981-1986 (Box 3)
  - Nicaragua - Brigade, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Miskitos, approximately 1984 (Box 4)
  - Nicaragua Election Resources and Originals, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
  - Photograph: James Douglas Speaking to Attendees at Unidentified Event, approximately 1980-1991 (Box 4)
  - Nicaragua Elections, approximately 1984 (Box 5)
  - Documents relating to U.S. Policies and Actions in Grenada, approximately 1984 (Box 5)
  - Deposition under Oral Examination of Manuel Torres, March 14, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Documents relating to U.S. Policy in Central America--The U.S. Position (Box 5)
  - Documents relating to U.S. Policies and Actions in El Salvador (Box 5)
  - Documents relating to U.S. Policies and Actions in Nicaragua (Box 5)
  - Attorney Letters (Box 5)
  - Lawyer-Program-Wits (Box 5)
  - Tribunal, approximately 1985 (Box 5)
  - Tribunal, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Post-Tribunal (Box 5)
- Video Tapes, 1984-1985
  - Citizens' Tribunal, January 19, 1985; 4 videotapes
  - Howard Heiner-United Methodist: Missionary Interview in Nicaragua, November 11, 1984; 1 videotape
  - Charlie Clements Bombings, Tribunals, 1 videotape